

# Rafael Garcia-Dias

Curriculum Vitae

# Research

2018-present Research associate, King's College London, Institute of Psychiatry, Psychol-

ogy & Neuroscience - IoPPN.

Supervisors Andrea Mechelli

Description Brain-based disorders represent 10.4% of the global burden of disease. Artificial Intelligence (AI) applications on neuroimaging have the potential of improving the detection and treatment of these disorders. Substantial progress has been made in showing the potential of AI in diagnosis and prognosis on controlled setups. However, the real-world implementation of these techniques is limited by differences in sensitivity among equipment and scanning protocols. This issue, known as scanner bias, means that diagnostic and prognostic AI applications developed using images from a certain machine tend to perform poorly when applied to images from different machines. I am the developer of Neuroharmony, an AI-based solution for this problem.

#### Education

2015–2018 PhD in Astrophysics, Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias - IAC.

2013–2015 Masters of Physics, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul - UFRGS.

2013 Physics Degree, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul - UFRGS.

### PhD Thesis

Title Machine learning in high resolution spectroscopy

Supervisors Allende Prieto & Sanchez Almeida

Description The data volume generated by many existing and forthcoming astronomical instruments is simply too large for traditional analysis techniques. Two extreme cases are the Large Synoptic Survey Telescope (LSST) and the Gaia mission. In stellar astrophysics, the legacy of the M-K spectroscopic classification scheme is undeniable. Despite its limitations, this system continues to be used today, but with the advent of massive spectroscopic surveys, the time is ripe to find a replacement. The MK system is a supervised classification algorithm based on spectral features easily identifiable by a human on a medium-resolution stellar spectrum. The system does not make any explicit connection to atmospheric parameters of the stars, such as effective temperature or surface gravity, making it independent from ever-changing physical models. Any future alternative should retain that property, and ideally be unsupervised, i.e. adopt natural groupings of stars, rather that ad hoc criteria. In this PhD project we are trying to explore machine learning algorithms to address this question.

#### Masters Dissertation

Title Spectroscopy and photometry of open clusters – Understanding the Galaxy chemical evolution

Supervisors Professor Charles Bonatto & Professor Alan Alves-Brito

Description

The formation and evolution of the Galaxy is still poorly understood. As chemical abundance ratios are proportional to crucial variables such as the star formation rate and the time-scale of chemical enrichment, a key observable to constrain the Galactic evolution model is the variation of the chemical abundances across the Galactic disk. Many studies were done in this area to date, but there is systematic abundance differences among them due to inhomogeneities on the adopted methodologies. We aim to homogeneously analyse, photometric and spectroscopically, a sample of 60 open clusters to trace a reliable chemical profile of the Galactic disk. For this purpose we developed a python routine for automatically acquire stellar atmospheric parameters and chemical abundances based on 2013 version of MOOG (Sneden 1973) and Kurucz models (Castelli et al. 1997).

# Publication List

R, Garcia-Dias scholar.google.com/citations?user=MlwZerQAAAAJ, Complete list of publications - google scholar.

#### Courses

ESAC DATA ANALYSIS & STATISTICS WORKSHOP 2017: Nov. 28 -

Dec 01, Covered fundamental topics in statistics and data analysis, including practical 2017 applications and advanced topics.

London – United Kingdom

- Nov. 13 17, XXIX Canary Islands Winter School of Astrophysics on Applications 2017 of Radiative Transfer to Stellar and Planetary Atmospheres: advanced school dedicated to the fundamental physical processes in both stellar and planetary atmospheres, as well as the bases of the numerical treatment of radiative transfer, to form researchers with the background required to face the present and future challenges.
- Oct. 02 03, Early Data Release and Scientific Exploitation of the J-PLUS Survey: 2017 The goal of the event was to present the survey to the Spanish community, describe the potential and quality of the data, and discuss scientific cases and applications.
  - July 22-29, SDSS-IV Collaboration Meeting Santiago 2017: The Sloan community 2017 meeting. The talks in the conference covered topics in galactic, extragalactic, cosmology and technical aspects of the infrastructure of the Sloan Digital Sky Survey.
- Sept. 12 16, 11th Heidelberg Summer School on the topic of Astrostatistics & 2016 **Data Mining:** The school looked at the principles of inference and methods of astronomical data analysis and data mining, also covering a range of numerical and statistical techniques and their application to different types of astronomical data.
- Conference on Big Data from Space BiDS'16: The objective of this Mar. 15 - 17, 2016 conference is to bring together researchers, engineers and users working in the area of Big Data from Space.
  - Aug. 18-21, ALMA and the Brazilian community workshop: The goal of the 2014 workshop was to explore how the current science activity within the Brazilian community can benefit from the new ALMA observatory and millimeter/submm observations in general.
- Sept. 02 12, JPL-Caltech Virtual Summer School in Big Data Analytics: Compu-2014 tational skills and methodology needed for the analysis and interpretation of ever more massive and complex data sets are essential for the scientific and technological workforce in the 21st century. This virtual summer school addressed this need.
- Out. 18 19, VIII workshop in neuroscience: the workshop covered the themes mem-2014 ory, consciousness, neurotoxicity, neurodegeneracy and graduate programs in neuroscience. Bento Gonçalves, RS - Brasil. (UFRGS)
- Out. 28 29, III symposium of the UFRGS psychiatry league: controversial issue 2014 on neuroscience. In the symposium the following themes was discussed: neuroimaging, drug regulation, suiciding and medicalization.
- Sept. 16 20, **5th INPE advanced course:** An overview of cosmology in the era of large telescopes: Theory, observation and simulations. The lectures were focused on the following topics: 1) Cosmic Microwave Background, with emphasis on the new results from Planck 2) the large scale structure as unveiled by the recently completed Sloan Digital Sky Survey and 3) cosmological simulations, which became an essential part of the research in this field.

# Communication Skills

- 2017 Plenary talk at SDSS-IV Collaboration Meeting Santiago, presentation link
- 2017 Imparted a workshop in IATEX collaborative tools as overleaf and sharelatex and publications management with Mendeley at Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias.
- 2017 Imparted a workshop in version control using git, github, atom and gitkraken at Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias.
- 2016 Oral presentation at Día de Nuestra Ciencia
- 2014 Oral Presentation at ALMA and the Brazilian Community Workshop, at Rio de Janeiro, RJ - Brazil (ON).
- 2013 Poster at Latin American Regional IAU Meeting, at Florianopolis, RS Brazil
- 2010 2013 Oral and poster presentation at the annual scientific initiation meeting, at Porto Alegre, RS - Brazil (UFRGS)

# Computer skills

- Advanced Python (numpy, scikit-learn, matplotlib, pandas, astropy, h5py, ipyvolume, pandas, Jupyter-notebook, Spyder...), VIM, DS9, ALADIN, SHELL SCRIPT, LINUX, MOOG, LATEX.
- Intermediate IRAF, Git, Github, Computer Hardware and Support, Microsoft office, OpenOffice, SQL
  - Basic TensorFlow, C, FORTRAN, IDL, SCILAB, R, HTML, javaScript, TopCat

# Experience

#### Vocational

2017 Observations at the INT, La Palma.

10 nights performing spectroscopic observations at the Isaac Newton Telescope.

- Spectroscopic observations of stars (extreme metal poor candidates). The 10 nights were divided in two runs of 5 nights each.
- 2015 Observations at the NOT, La Palma.

6 nights making spectroscopic observations at the Nordic Optical Telescope.

#### Details:

- Spectroscopic observations of star in open clusters.
- 2010–2011 Intern, Magnetism Laboratory, UFRGS.

Developing experiments in nanotechnology related with giant magnetoresistance.

#### Details:

- Making nanotips by electrolysis
- Using sputtering to make multilayer nanofilms
- Building experimental apparatus

# 2011–2013 Intern, Astrophysics laboratory, UFRGS.

Studying open Clusters

#### Details:

- Measuring star formation rate in solar neighborhood
- SOAR photometry in clusters within the bridge between Magellanic clouds
- Creating a pipeline to perform photometry in VVV (VISTA Variables in The Via Lactea) tiles

## Miscellaneous

#### 2010–2013 **Teaching**.

- Private tutor:
  - Spanish
  - Physics
  - Math
- Euroschool Informatics
- Wizard Spanish

# Languages

Portuguese Native language

Spanish Advanced FluentEnglish Advanced Fluent